A Finding Aid to the Elaine Marie de Kooning papers, circa 1959-1988, in the Archives of American Art AAA.dekoelas
Archives of American Art
Elaine Marie de Kooning papers
circa 1959-1988
AAA.dekoelas
Archives of American Art
0.7 Linear feet
The Elaine Marie de Kooning papers are dated circa 1959-1988 and measure 0.7 linear feet. Two scrapbooks contain printed material, letters, and photographs that document de Kooning's protest against the death penalty and efforts to save the life of convicted criminal Caryl Chessman. There are 13 transcripts of interviews of Elaine de Kooning, conversations between de Kooning and others, and lectures by de Kooning. Also found are photographs, clippings, and 2 wooden Easter eggs sent by the White House to de Kooning to be decorated and returned. There is also an unprocessed addition that includes letters and postcards, subject files relating to de Kooning's portrait of president John F. Kennedy, photographs of de Kooning and others, additional writings, and a home recording sound disc of Willem de Kooning whistling.
De Kooning, Elaine
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated to the Archives of American Art in 2003 by Denise Lassaw, de Kooning's goddaughter and her mother Ernestine Lassaw, and in 2013-2015 by Denise Lassaw. Interview transcripts and lectures were donated in 2015 by Doris Aach, an artist who transcribed them for de Kooning.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original materials requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Elaine de Kooning (1918-1989) was an Abstract Expressionist painter, teacher and writer who lived and worked in New York City and East Hampton, N.Y.
Born in Brooklyn, New York, de Kooning studied briefly at Hunter College before enrolling at the Leonardo da Vinci Art School in New York City. She had her first solo exhibition in 1952 at the Stable Gallery in New York and has paintings in the permanent collections of the Museum of Modern Art, the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum and other institutions. She taught at Yale University, Carnegie Mellon Institute, University of Pennsylvania and other colleges and art schools. Elaine de Kooning died of lung cancer in 1989 at Southampton Hospital in Southampton, New York. Willem de Kooning, her husband of 48 years, survived her.
Scope and Contents note
The Elaine Marie de Kooning papers are dated circa 1959-1988 and measure 0.7 linear feet. Two scrapbooks contain printed material, letters, and photographs that document de Kooning's protest against the death penalty and efforts to save the life of convicted criminal Caryl Chessman. There are 13 transcripts of interviews of Elaine de Kooning, conversations between de Kooning and others, and lectures by de Kooning. Also found are photographs, clippings, and 2 wooden Easter eggs sent by the White House to de Kooning to be decorated and returned.
An unprocessed addition includes includes letters and postcards to Elaine de Kooning, subject files relating to de Kooning's portrait of president John F. Kennedy, a price list of drawings, photographs of de Kooning and others, additional writings and photocopies of letters about Willem de Kooning by Mercedes Matter, Ernestine Lawson and others, published serigraphs from the California Institute of Arts, and a. Also included is a home recording sound disc of Willem de Kooning whistling.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 2 series:
Series 1: Scrapbooks, circa 1959-1962 (Boxes 1-2: 0.4 linear ft.)
Series 2: Interviews, Conversations, and Lectures, 1978-1988 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Related Archival Materials note
Among the holding of the Archives is an oral history interview conducted in 1981 by Phyllis Tuchman, for the Archives of American Art's Mark Rothko and His Times oral history project. Also found is a collection of Elaine and Willem de Kooning financial records.
Chessman, Caryl, 1921-1960; De Kooning, Willem, 1904-; Artists--Political activity; Capital punishment; Interviews; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Transcripts
- Scrapbooks, circa 1959-1962; Series 1; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 1-2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Two scrapbooks, compiled by Elaine de Kooning, pertain to her effort to save the life of convicted criminal, Caryl Chessman, and her protest against the death penalty. Volume 1 "The Chessman Story" contains clippings. Volume 2 includes a copy of Chessman's 16 page letter to Governor Edmund G. Brown, clippings concerning efforts to save Chessman, de Kooning's speech notes for political rallies, her correspondence with attorney Rosalie Asher, and photographs of members of the art community involved with this cause.
  - Scrapbook, Volume 1, "The Chessman Story", circa 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, Volume 2, circa 1960 (Box 2)
- Interviews, Conversations, and Lectures, 1978-1988; Series 2; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  There are 13 transcripts of audio interviews of Elaine de Kooning; conversations between de Kooning and others; and lectures by de Kooning (also included is a CD containing Word files of the transcripts and a jpeg of a note to Doris Aach from Elaine de Kooning concerning her “first piece of sculpture,” and a jpeg of that sculpture). The interviews, conversations, and lectures were transcribed by Doris Aach for Elaine de Kooning, who planned to use them for a book.
  - CD, undated; 1 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    CD contains Word files of the printed transcripts, a jpeg note to Doris Aach from Elaine de Kooning concerning her "first piece of sculpture"; and a second jpeg image of that sculpture.
  - Transcripts of Interviews of de Kooning (Box 1)
    - Conducted by Amei Wallach, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Conducted by Lyn Kienholz, KRW radio, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Conducted by Charles Hayes, for a book "Pearl in the Mud", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Conducted by Molly Barnes, KPFK radio, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Transcripts of Recorded Conversations (Box 1)
    - Between de Kooning, Unidentified Person, and Ellen Auerbach, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Between de Kooning and Koos Lassooy, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Between de Kooning and Minna Daniels, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Between de Kooning and Antonia Zara, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Between de Kooning, Michael and Mildred Lowe, and Judith (last name unknown), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Between Elaine de Kooning and Bill de Kooning, and Tully and Gladys Filmus, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Between de Kooning and Arthur Tobler, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Transcript of Lecture on Willem de Kooning by Elaine de Kooning, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Transcript of Lecture by de Kooning About Her Life and Work, C.F.S. Hancock Lecture, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)